welcome to AP US History unit 1 this
unit covers the Americas before
Europeans arrived and what happened
after they arrived this unit is worth 4
to 6% on your AP exam that doesn't mean
you shouldn't study it but you might
want to study other units a little
harder this video is simply a clip
together video of all of my topic videos
without the questions if you like to
view my topic videos that have AP style
questions and answers on them the
playlist will be in the description
enough for me though let's get into it
topic would .2 is all about Societies in
the Americas before the contact of
Europeans on the continent the starting
thing to know is that before Europeans
came into contact with America there
were many societies that existed
inhabited by various Native American
tribes for this video you need to know
how they lived in the Americas the crop
of maze or corn became a staple food of
many of these native societies
especially the ones in the southwest as
the cultivation of maze taught these
societies advanced irrigation techniques
and supported Economic Development what
the most notable tribes thriving from
this was the hakam who built extensive
Canal systems for irrigation and the
Great Basin and the Western Great Plains
many tribes saw the dryness in the area
and lived by always moving around and
not making permanent settlements
examples of tribes in this area were the
Ute and the Shani tribes the Northeast
was much different the Atlantic and the
Mississippi River allowed for permanent
villages to be made with the societies
functioning on agricultural obligations
and hunter gatherers a notable tribe in
in this area was the Cahokia and this
was actually very similar to the people
in the Northeast in present day
California area as they also supported
themselves on hunting and Gathering and
use the Pacific Shoreline as a good
place to build settlements with one of
my favorite tribes in this area being
the shin so on our last video we talked
on Societies in the Americas before
Europeans came in contact well Mr
Christopher Columbus arrives onto
America in 1492 and that changes the way
of history for the Americas forever
essentially the various year European
countries decided that they were going
to explore and Conquest this new land
the reasons for this are very simple
it's the 3 G's gold God and Glory first
Europeans wanted to gain more wealth
which was at the time measured in gold
and silver under a system called merism
since there was a lot of gold in the
Americas conquering land allowed for
mines to open up and more wealth going
to European countries the second reason
was that Europeans saw the native
civilizations in the new world and felt
a kind of religious o ation to spread
and convert the natives to Christianity
with a special effort from Jesuit
missionaries finally there was Glory
back then the more land a country
controlled the more powerful it was
considered the Americas offered a new
frontier to claim and show off to the
rest of the world and that's pretty much
1.4 is all about the Colombian Exchange
and how it impacted Europe and the
Americas so first we need to define the
Columbian Exchange by definition the
Colombian Exchange means the transfer of
goods Foods animals for a fauna diseases
and slaves between the Americas and
Europe after European contact in the
Americas essentially what happened is
when European countries came to America
various things got transferred from one
continent to the other the Americas had
revolutionary crops like maze potatoes
tomatoes and tobacco that got
transferred to Europe the influx of
these foods to Europe caused there to be
a population boom and the transfer of
goods allowed for Europe to shift from
an economic system of feudalism where
land was owned by Nobles and worked by
peasants to capitalism where trade and
Industry are controlled by private
owners for profit also during this time
Maritime Technologies underwent massive
improvements such as the caravel and
astrola meaning it was easier for people
to explore what also made it easier was
the impation of joint stock companies
this was a company that a bunch of
people could pull their money into so if
it did well they would all earn money if
not they could only lose their initial
investment so it was very low risk these
joint stock companies were the companies
funding these voyages to the Americas as
for Europe's effect on the Americas yes
there was Goods foods and animals
brought to the Americas like wheat rice
horses and pigs but the biggest thing
that came from Europe to the Americas
was deadly diseases Europeans had been
living with diseases like small poox and
measles for many centuries and had
gained a sort of natural immunity to
them the natives however did not have
the same immunity and therefore when
these diseases got introduced it's said
that 50 to 90% of the native population
died died because of them and that's all
1.5 is all about slavery in the New
World by the Spanish in my last video I
didn't go much into detail on this but
along with Goods foods and diseases
slaves were also transported during the
Colombian Exchange the reason for this
was well we first need to go back in
time when the Spanish landed in the new
world they wanted to harvest the goods
and crops of the land and therefore
decided to enslave the natives through
the encomienda system this was a system
where Spanish conquistadors were granted
the right to extract labor from the
indigenous people living in a particular
area in return the conquistadors were to
provide the natives in this area with
religious Christian guidance and take
care of their welfare however in
practice these obligations were often
neglected and poorly fulfilled this
enslaving of the natives wouldn't end up
working though for two reasons first the
natives knew the land that they had
lived on for centuries better than their
European guests and therefore could
Escape pretty easily and second the
natives were dying in Mass numbers by
small poox and you can't enslave a dead
person the way Spain solved this was by
transporting slaves from Africa to the
new world on ships with the brutal
Journey known as the Middle Passage and
work the land this solved both problems
because the Africans wouldn't know the
land and they have the same natural
immunity to small pox that Europeans did
with these many Africans on the
continent it allowed for a cast system
to form known as the Casta system where
Natives and Africans were on the bottom
and anyone with Spanish blood was on the
top we'll be going into more detail on
the African slave trade in a future
video for now that's all 1.6 is all
about different views in the world
during this time along with some
organized military resistances so it's
fair to say that any time in history
when an existing culture interacts with
a new culture misinterpretations and
profiling will always happen from both
sides in terms of the natives and
Europeans their cultures had different
world views on religion gender roles
family land use and power over time
Europeans and Native Americans adopted
some useful aspects of each other's
culture but as Europeans increasingly
attempted to enslave the natives
different military defenses from the
natives happened a few examples of this
were the kapol uprising in the yakatan
and the Teno rebellion in the Caribbean
and even though documents like the rera
miendo tried to justify harsh treatments
of the natives it sparked debates from
around the continent of how Africans and
Native Americans should be treated
though these arguments did exist any
arguments often led to Europeans
justifying their treatment of Africans
and the natives using culture or as an
answer unfortunately that is most of
what early US history is about thank you
for watching please check the
description for more help and I'll see
you in unit 2